

COMPUTER SCIENCE P.H.D CANDIDATE INTERESTED IN THE APPLICATION OF NLP METHODS IN COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCE

💌 indira.sen@rwth-aachen.de | 🌴 https://indiiigo.github.io/ | 🖸 Indiiigo | 💆 @indiiigosky | Google Scholar

Research Interests

I'm interested in improving the measurement of psychosocial constructs, including political and prejudicial attitudes and behaviors, from digital trace data using mixed methods and natural language processing. My research aims to illuminate and characterize the potentials, pitfalls, and consequences of understanding such attitudes from unobtrusive digital traces.

Education

RWTH-Aachen and GESIS - Leibnitz Institute for Social Sciences

Cologne, Germany

Ph.D in Computer Science (Magna cum Laude)

ADVISORS: PROF. CLAUDIA WAGNER, PROF. WIL VAN DER AALST

Oct, 2018 - Apr, 2024

Indraprastha Institute of Information Technology (IIIT-D)

M.S IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

New Delhi, India Aug, 2015 - Dec, 2017

ADVISOR: PROF. PONNURANGAM KUMARAGURU (PK)

GPA: 8.67/10

Vellore Institute of Technology (VIT)

B.S IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

GPA: 9.1/10

Jul, 2010 - May, 2014

Vellore, India

Experience

University of Konstanz

Konstanz, Germany

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER, DEPARTMENT OF POLITICAL SCIENCE AND PUBLIC ADMINISTRATION. ADVISOR: PROF. DAVID

GARCIA

Oct 2023 -

- Research: Designing and Evaluating Interventions against Harmful Online Communication
- Teaching: 1) The Social Informatics of Large Language Models, 2) Introduction to Python

Computational Social Science Department, GESIS

DOCTORAL RESEARCHER. ADVISORS: PROF. CLAUDIA WAGNER, DR. KATRIN WELLER

Cologne, Germany
Oct 2018 - Sept 2023

- · Identifying, Characterizing and Quantifying errors that occur when measuring attitudes from Digital Traces
- Building robust and interpretable NLP methods for measuring social science phenomena
- Large scale Twitter data collection using Amazon Web Services (AWS) as a service for Social Scientists.

Snap Inc. Santa Monica, USA

RESEARCH INTERN, COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCE. ADVISOR: Dr. FRANCESCO BARBIERI

Jul 2022 - Oct 2022

• Developing a Stakeholder-centred Framework for Multilingual Sensitive Content Detection

Nokia Bell Labs Cambridge, UK (virtual)

INTERN AT SOCIAL DYNAMICS GROUP. ADVISOR: DR. DANIELE QUERCIA

Jun 2021 - Aug 2021

- · Understanding and Characterizing the sustainability efforts of companies from employee reviews.
- Developed mixed-method techniques for detecting employees' views on their employer's sustainability efforts using a deep-learning framework (SBERT)
- Results from the internship were published at CSCW'22 and IEEE Vis'22.

SAGE Ocean London, UK (virtual)

SAGE Ocean Fellow. Advisor: Dr. Daniela Duca

Oct 2020 - Dec 2020

- Contributing to a Text cleaning WebApp called Texti
- Working on NLP transformations in Python and documentation
- Results from the Fellowship are described here.

Precog Research Lab, IIIT Delhi

New Delhi, India

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE. ADVISORS: PROF. PONNURANGAM KUMARAGURU AND PROF. ARUN BALAJI BUDURU

Dec 2017 - Aug 2018

- Landscaping the fake like marketplace on Instagram and characterizing fake likers, and their attack vectors.
- · Detecting Multimodal Hatespeech on Social Media

May 6, 2024 Indira Sen · CV

CHILI Lab, École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

SUMMER INTERN, ADVISOR: PROF. PIERRE DILLENBOURG

· Worked on inferring dependencies between EPFL courses based on Concept Mining and grading patterns

Nanyang Technological University

Singapore

RESEARCH ASSISTANT, ADVISOR: PROF. ANWITAMAN DUTTA

Jan 2017- May 2017

Jun 2017- Aug 2017

• Master's Thesis: Worked on detecting fake engagement on Instagram.

Grants

2022	Grant for Organizing the 'Conference on Harmful Online Communication' , Co-Applicant, 20,000 EUR	Fritz Thyssen Foundation, Germany
	Grant for the Project 'Not one bit sexist: A competitive game against sexist language' , For creating a	
2022	gamified crowdsourcing platform to collect perceptions of sexism from a diverse group of people.	Meta (Facebook)
	Co-Applicant, 10,000 EUR	
2020	Travel Grant, For attending EMNLP, 200 EUR	virtual
2020	Travel Grant, For attending FAT* 2020, 1500 EUR	Barcelona, Spain
2019	Travel Grant, For attending Summer Institute in Computational Social Science (SICCS), 1000 EUR	Bamberg, Germany

Honors & Awards ____

2023	Research Award for Best Paper by a Doctoral Researcher , Chosen by the GESIS Scientific Board from 40+ doctoral candidates	GESIS
2022	Research Award for Interdepartmental Collaboration, for interdisciplinary research collaborations	GESIS
2021	Summer Intern Award for Outstanding Innovation, Nokia Bell Labs	Cambridge, UK / virtual
2021- 2023	Best Reviewer Award, ICWSM (2021, 20222, 2023), The WebConf (2023)	
2020	Selected for SAGE Text-Mining Fellowship, SAGE, Ocean	London, UK (virtual)
2020	Selected as Facilitator for the Alan Turing Institute Data Study Group, 2 week hackathon where we	virtual
2020	worked with an Industry partner (CatsAI) to deploy explainable AI predictions	VIILUAL
2017	Nomination for Best Master's Thesis, 5 among 20+ theses in the Computer Science Department	IIIT-Delhi, India
2017	TA Excellence Award, Foundations of Computer Security	IIIT-Delhi, India
2017	Accepted to Summer@EPFL, One of 60 interns selected out of 2000 applications	EPFL, Switzerland
2015-	Deanle Marit Liet Fox Academic Parformance	IIIT-Delhi, India
2016	Dean's Merit List, For Academic Performance	III I-Deliii, Iiidid
2015	GATE Scholarship, Scholarship for Master's Studies	
2011- 2014	Merit Scholarship, For Outstanding Academic Achievement in 4 years of Bachelor's studies	VIT, Vellore

Publications

Journal Articles

Insider Stories: Analyzing Internal Sustainability Efforts of Major US Companies from	2023
Online Reviews.	2023

Indira Sen, Daniele Quercia, Licia Capra, Matteo Montecchi, and Sanja Šćepanović. Humanities and Social Sciences Communications 10, no. 1 (2023): 1-9.

Depression at Work: Exploring Depression in Major US Companies from Online Reviews.

2022

Indira Sen, Daniele Quercia, Marios Constantinides, Matteo Montecchi, Licia Capra, Sanja Scepanovic, and Renzo Bianchi.

PROCEEDINGS OF THE ACM ON HUMAN-COMPUTER INTERACTION. TO BE PRESENTED AT THE 25TH ACM CONFERENCE ON COMPUTER-SUPPORTED COOPERATIVE WORK AND SOCIAL COMPUTING (CSCW)

Visualizing Internal Sustainability Efforts in Big Companies.

2022

CHIARA CECCARINI, EDYTA PAULINA BOGUCKA, **INDIRA SEN**, MARIOS CONSTANTINIDES, CATIA PRANDI, AND DANIELE QUERCIA. IEEE COMPUTER GRAPHICS AND APPLICATIONS

	Conference Articles
202	People Make Better Edits: Measuring the Efficacy of LLM-generated Counterfactually Augmented Data for Harmful Language Detection
То арре	INDIRA SEN, DENNIS ASSENMACHER, MATTIA SAMORY, ISABELLE AUGENSTEIN, WIL VAN DER AALST, AND CLAUDIA WAGNER. CONFERENCE ON EMPIRICAL METHODS ON NATURAL LANGUAGE PROCESSING (EMNLP)
202	Counterfactually Augmented Data and Unintended Bias: The Case of Sexism and Hate Speech Detection
short pap	INDIRA SEN, MATTIA SAMORY, CLAUDIA WAGNER AND ISABELLE AUGENSTEIN. ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF THE NORTH AMERICAN CHAPTER OF THE ASSOCIATION FOR COMPUTATIONAL LINGUISTICS (NAACL)
20.	How Does Counterfactually Augmented Data Impact Models for Social Computing Constructs?
	INDIRA SEN, MATTIA SAMORY, FABIAN FLOECK, CLAUDIA WAGNER AND ISABELLE AUGENSTEIN. CONFERENCE ON EMPIRICAL METHODS ON NATURAL LANGUAGE PROCESSING (EMNLP)
20.	"Call me sexist, but": Revisiting Sexism Detection Using Psychological Scales and Adversarial Samples
	MATTIA SAMORY, INDIRA SEN, JULIAN KOHNE, FABIAN FLOECK, AND CLAUDIA WAGNER. INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON WEB AND SOCIAL MEDIA (ICWSM)
202	On the Reliability and Validity of Detecting Approval of Political Actors in Tweets INDIRA SEN, FABIAN FLOECK, AND CLAUDIA WAGNER.
	CONFERENCE ON EMPIRICAL METHODS ON NATURAL LANGUAGE PROCESSING (EMNLP)
20	Empowering First Responders through Automated Multimodal Content Moderation
Best Paper Awa	Divam Gupta, Indira Se n, Niharika Sachdeva, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru, Arun Balaji Buduru. IEEE International Conference on Cognitive Computing
20	Worth its Weight in Likes: Towards Detecting Fake Likes on Instagram
short pap	Indira Sen, Anupama Aggarwal, Shiven Mian, Siddharth Singh, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru, Anwitaman Datta. WebSci
	Workshop Articles
202	The End of the Rehydration Era The Problem of Sharing Harmful Twitter Research Data
Best Paper Awa	DENNIS ASSENMACHER, INDIRA SEN , LEON FRÖHLING, CLAUDIA WAGNER NEATCLASS, IN CONJUNCTION WITH ICWSM
20.	What Human Rationales Tell us about Machine Explanations
	INDIRA SEN, MATTIA SAMORY, FABIAN FLOECK, CLAUDIA WAGNER HCI+NLP WORKSHOP, IN CONJUNCTION WITH EACL
202	Measuring Public Opinion Online: Potentials and Pitfalls
Post	INDIRA SEN, FABIAN FLOECK, CLAUDIA WAGNER WOMEN IN MACHINE LEARNING (WIML), IN CONJUNCTION WITH NEURIPS
20	A Twitter Corpus for Hindi-English Code Mixed POS Tagging
Data Pap	Kushagra Singh, Indira Sen, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru. Workshop on Natural Language Processing for Social Media (SocialNLP), In conjunction with ACL
20	Language Identification and Named Entity Recognition in Hinglish Code Mixed Tweets Kushagra Singh, Indira Sen, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru. ACL Student Research Workshop

2021

Milan, Italy (virtual)

Nov 2023

A Total Error Framework for Digital Traces of Human Behavior on Online Platforms

INDIRA SEN, FABIAN FLOECK, KATRIN WELLER, BERND WEISS, AND CLAUDIA WAGNER.

Theory-driven NLP

BOCCONI UNIVERSITY

Social Media based Measurements of Psychosocial Phenomena: Potentials and Pitfalls

Düsseldorf, Germany

HEINRICH HEINE UNIVERSITY May 2022

Identifying and Mitigating Gender Bias in Algorithmic Systems

COLOGNE BUSINESS SCHOOL May 2022

A Total Error Framework for Digital Traces of Humans

Virtual Sep 2020

Cologne

DGS Kongress

(Mis)Measuring Attitudes from Digital Traces

Virtual

THIRD ANNUAL POLITICS AND COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCES CONFERENCE (PACSS)

Aug 2020

Teaching

Introduction to Programming with Python

Konstanz, Germany

University of Konstanz

Oct 2023

Introduction to Python Block Course at the University of Konstanz (16.10-20.10, Winter Semester 2023/2024)

The Social Informatics of Large Language Models

Konstanz, Germany

UNIVERSITY OF KONSTANZ

Oct 2023 - Mar 2024

• Co-teaching a seminar course on the impact of Large Language Models om Society with practical hands-on sessions.

Social Research with Social Media Data: Potentials and Pitfalls.

GESIS, Cologne, Germany

GESIS

2020-2022

• Tutorial on diagnosing errors and biases in observational studies from digital traces

Translation Tutorial on the Total Error Paradigm for Social Inferences

Barcelona, Spain

Jan 2020

FAT* 2020

• Tutorial on diagnosing errors and biases in observational studies from digital traces

Introduction to Python and Data Science with Python

Cologne, Germany Oct, 2019

University of Cologne

• Interactive, hands-on five-day lecture series for teaching introductory python concepts to social science doctoral candidates

Teaching Assistant New Delhi, India

IIIT DELHI

2015 - 2017

- Linear Algebra
- · Foundations of Computer Security

Academic Service and Mentorship

Tutorials Co-chair

INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON WEB AND SOCIAL MEDIA (ICWSM'24)

Workshop Organizer

DOCUMENTING WEB DATA FOR SOCIAL RESEARCH (#DOCUWEB22), CO-LOCATED WITH WEBSCI'22

Workshop Organizer

PARTICIPATORY DEVELOPMENT OF QUALITY GUIDELINES FOR SOCIAL MEDIA RESEARCH, CO-LOCATED WITH ICWSM'21

Reviewing

РС мемвек

TheWebConf (2023, 2024), EMNLP (2023), ICWSM (2021, 2022, 2023), ACL Student Research Workshop (2020, 2021, 2022), WikiWorkshop (2022), HCI+NLP workshop (2022)

REVIEWER

CSCW (2019, 2020), TheWebconf (2020, 2021), EMNLP (2020), ACL Rolling Review (2021, 2022, 2023), EPJ Data Science (2022)

Mentorship

SUPERVISED OR CO-SUPERVISED THESES

- Esi Doda (RWTH Aachen). Master's Thesis. Racial Disparities in Social Media Commentary about Football
- Vani Agarwal (IIIT-D). Master's Thesis. Improving Content Moderation through Co-Training
- Kushagra Singh (IIIT-D). Bachelor's Thesis. Information Extraction Tools for Code-Mixed Hindi-English Social Media Content

Skills_

Programming: Python, R, Java, C++, C, MongoDB, SQL, Bash

Programming Libraries/Tools: scikit-learn, pytorch, tensorflow, huggingface, transformers, keras, pandas, NLTK, NetworkX, Amazon Web Services

Surveys: Amazon Mechanical Turk, Prolific, Qualtrics, LimeSurvey

Natural Languages: English (fluent, C2), German (intermediate, B1), Hindi (fluent), Bengali (native)